[Music]
the first randomized prospective
clinical evaluation of the effects of
fasting on chemotherapy the incidence of
chemotherapy induced nain vomiting in
cancer patients was published in 2014
but the patients were dogs cancer
bearing dogs presenting at a veterinary
hospital where randomized to be fasted
for 24 hours before chemotherapy and
those that were were significantly less
likely to suffer from vomiting only one
in 10 compared to two out of three in
the non-fasted group which is great but
what can that tell us about human
medicine evidently not much it's nearly
impossible to rely on most animal data
to predict whether or not an
intervention will have a favorable
clinical benefit risk ratio in human
subjects for example mice have a
metabolic rate approximately seven times
higher than humans so a single day of
fasting can cut lean body mass about
15% that would take over a month of
fasting in people uh so that dramatic
study on mice showing 100% alive versus
100% dead on high do chemo depending on
whether they were faster for 60 hours
what can that really tell us and when it
comes to cancer rodents can bear massive
tumor loads whereas people uh generally
waste weight and die when tumor masses
reach just a thousandth of our body
weight you can't even necessarily
extrapolate from one rat to another even
within the same strain bought from
different dealers the only way to see
what happens in humans the only way to
guarantee findings IR relevant is to
study people the theory is that
combining fasting Cycles with
chemotherapy could extend the survival
of advanced stage cancer patients by
both retarding tumor progress ression
and reducing side effects or even
providing an alternative to chemotherapy
altogether an early stage cancer
patients but uh that's all contingent on
it being confirmed in human clinical
trials first there were Cas series
several patients diagnosed with a
variety of cancers elected to undertake
fasting prior to chemotherapy and shared
their experiences those who underwent
chemo both with and without fasting
reported a reduction of fatigue weakness
and gastrointestinal side effects while
fasting in fact felt better across the
board with zero vomiting in the fasting
group uh the weight loss during the
first few days of fasting was rapidly
recovered in most of the patients and
did not lead to any detectable harm so
overall was looking feasible safe with
the potential to ameliorate side effects
but only randomized clinical studies
could tell for sure and so here we go
breast and ovarian cancer patients fast
in starting 36 hours before and ending
24 hours after chemotherapy and it did
appear to improve the quality of life
and fatigue but another study found no
such beneficial effects there did appear
to perhaps be less bone marot toxicity
given the higher counts of red blood
cells and platelet making cells but no
benefit when it came to killing off
white blood cells the immune system
cells so that was a disappointment
perhaps they didn't fast long enough
they only fasted 24 hours before and
after to find out the optimal duration
20 cancer patients were split up into
three groups fasting for 24 48 or a
total of 72 hours all those in the
24-hour group suffered nausea after
chemo but less than half in the 72-hour
group and most were vomiting in the
24-hour group but none in the longest
fasting group longer fasting groups also
tend to suffer less nerve damage damage
and less serious bone marrow suppression
even after 24 hours of fasting two
cycles of chemo can knock people's white
blood cells down to suboptimal levels
but with 72 hours chemo knocked their
immune system down but not out okay so
short-term fasting May reduce
chemotherapy induce toxicity but what I
want to know is if it makes it work
better a systematic review of 22 studies
found that overall fasting was found to
not only reduce chemotherapy side
effects like organ damage immune
suppression and chemotherapy induced
death but also to suppress tumor
progression including tumor growth and
metastases resulting in improved
survival but nearly all the studies were
done on lab animals the studies on
humans are limited to evaluating safety
and side effects the tumor suppression
effects of fasting for example its
influence on tumor growth metastases and
prognosis have not been evaluated
until now to be continued
[Music]